Guide to the John James Audubon Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John James Audubon collection
1823-1898
1826-1840
GEN MSS 829
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.46
(2 boxes)
The collection contains autograph letters, signed, written by John James Audubon to his wife Lucy Green Bakewell Audubon and colleagues, one of his engraved visiting cards, and autograph manuscript writings by Audubon and fellow naturalists Thomas McCulloch, Thomas Nuttall, and John Kirk Townsend. Prominent among the letters is one of 4,000 words from Audubon to his wife, written from Edinburgh in 1826, in which he describes exhibitions of his drawings and various social events, with a transcription of a phrenologist's reading that he had received. Also included are an 1898 letter from ornithologist Leonard C. Sanford to Sarah Manning Sage, the wife of collector Dean Sage, and a letter from John Woodhouse Audubon, son of John James Audubon, to A. J. Crossman. Prominent among the writings are 118 essays published in Audubon's Ornithological Biography (1831-39), describing plates included in his major work The Birds of America (1827-38), and an annotated pencil drawing of a petrel. Much of the material in the collection was formerly owned by William Robertson Coe.
Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Robertson Coe, Yale 1949 Hon., 1952-1954; Purchased from B. Tighe on the William Robertson Coe Fund, 1954; Purchased from Wormser on the William Robertson Coe Fund, 1955.
Custodial History
A large part of the collection was given to the library by William Robertson Coe (1869-1955), who also donated his ornithological books to Yale University.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Morris Tyler Family Collection of John James Audubon (GEN MSS 85)
John James Audubon (1785-1851)
American naturalist best known for his major work The Birds of America and The Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains letters written by John James Audubon to his wife and colleagues, one of his engraved visiting cards, and writings by Audubon and fellow naturalists Thomas McCulloch, Thomas Nuttall, and John Kirk Townsend. Prominent among the letters is a fair copy of two letters (4,000 words) from Audubon to his wife Lucy, written in Edinburgh in 1826, in which he describes the exhibition of his drawings and various social events in the city, with a transcription of a phrenologist's reading that he had received. Some of the letters are accompanied by typed transcriptions, and one includes an 1898 letter from ornithologist Leonard C. Sanford to the wife of collector Dean Sage. Prominent among the writings are some of Audubon's essays published as Ornithological Biography (1831-1839), describing plates included in his major work The Birds of America (1827-1838). Also included is one letter from Audubon's son, John Woodhouse Audubon to A. J. Crossman.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1823-1898. II. Writings, 1826-1835.
Birds -- North America; Natural history -- United States; Ornithologists -- United States; Ornithology -- United States; Petrels -- Pictorial works; Ornithologists -- 19th century -- United States; Abert, John James, 1788-1863; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851 ( Audubon's Birds of America); Audubon, John James, 1785-1851 ( Ornithological biography); Audubon, John Woodhouse, 1812-1862; Audubon, Lucy Green Bakewell, 1788-1874; Harlan, Richard, 1796-1843; Havell, Robert, 1793-1878; McCulloch, Thomas, 1776-1843; Nuttall, Thomas, 1786-1859; Rozier, Jean Ferdinand, 1777-1864; Sage, Sarah Manning, 1841-1915; Sanford, L. C. (Leonard Cutler), 1868-1950; Townsend, John Kirk, 1809-1851; Coe, William Robertson, 1869-1955 -- Ownership
- Correspondence, 1823-1898; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Letters from John James Audubon and Letter from John Woodhouse Audubon.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains letters from Audubon to his wife Lucy, and naturalists, printers, and business partners.
  - Letters from John James Audubon
    - To Lucy Audubon, 1826 Dec 21-22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      Autograph manuscript copy of two letters with bound typed transcription; transcription filed in Box 1, manuscript filed in Box 2
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of William Robertson Coe, Yale 1949 Hon.
    - To Lucy Audubon, 1828, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Purchased from Wormser on the William Robertson Coe Fund, 1955
      Autograph manuscript letter dated November 10, 1828, accompanied by engraved portrait of John James Audubon, after Chappel, 1851
    - To Richard Harlan, 1830, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Gift of William Robertson Coe, Yale 1949 Hon., 1953
      Autograph manuscript letter dated October 17 and 25, 1830, bound with typed transcription. Accompanied by an autograph manuscript letter from Harlan to John James Abert, November 25, 1837
    - To Robert Havell Jr., 1830 Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Autograph manuscript letter
      Gift of William Robertson Coe, Yale 1949 Hon., 1954
    - To Thomas McCulloch Jr., 1841 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Gift of J. W. Livermore, 1953
    - To Jean Ferdinand Rozier, 1823 Oct 14 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Purchased from B. Tighe on the William Robertson Coe Fund, 1954
    - To unidentified correspondent, regarding subscribers, 1840 Jan 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Autograph manuscript letter with typed transcriptions; accompanied by biographical clippings and an engraved portrait of Audubon by Cruickshank after Turner, 1835
    - Signature clipped from letter, 1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Removed from Audubon and his Journals, by Maria R. Audubon (1897); accompanied by autograph manuscript letter from Leonard C. Sanford to Sarah Manning Sage, September 22, 1898
    - Engraved visiting card for "Mr. Audubon" bearing on verso stamped wax seal with image of "Wild Turkey" plate from The Birds of America, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter from John Woodhouse Audubon
    - To A. J. Crossman, 1860 Feb 22 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Writings, 1826-1835; Series II; 14
  Series II is organized alphabetically.
  The series contains autograph manuscripts by Audubon composed for his publications relating to birds and quadrupeds. Interfiled with Audubon's own writings for his Ornithological Biography are several autograph manuscript entries by naturalists Thomas McCulloch (1776-1843), Thomas Nuttall (1786-1859), and John Kirk Townsend (1809-1851).
  - Ornithological Biography, 1835, undated
    Contains autograph manuscript descriptions of birds to accompany 118 plates contained in The Birds of America; the essays are arranged in order of plate number.
    Gift of William Robertson Coe, Yale 1949 Hon., 1952
  - Petrel, 1826 Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Graphite sketch of bird with autograph manuscript notes and description on recto and verso
  - Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Autograph manuscript notes for Part 10, plate 49, "Douglasses Spermophile" (Douglas's Marmot); the notes roughly correspond to volume 1, pages 373-76.
- Oversize
  - Letter from John James Audubon to Lucy Audubon, in Series I, 1826 Dec 21-22 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ornithological Biography, 1835, undated (Box 2, Folder 14-18)
    Sections published in volume 3, from red-throated diver through arctic tern, with unidentified drafts
  - Ornithological Biography, 1835, undated (Box 2, Folder 19-25)
    Sections published in volume 4, from American avocet through black-throated bunting, with "Observations on Our Smaller Thrushes" and unidentified drafts